Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated, bulk 1898-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Company Offices Series, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated, bulk 1920-2000, (83 boxes plus oversize containers)
  - Public Relations Subseries, 1911-2008 and undated, (13 boxes and oversize containers)
    [Box 70 contains some fragile material that is in need of preservation. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material, as contents may need to be photocopied before being handled.]
    - Advertising and Promotions Subseries, 1911-1998 and undated
      The bulk of the material dates from the 1980s and consists of bids, invoices, contracts, shipping lists, and correspondence regarding advertising in specific periodicals, radio stations, and television stations. Also included are memos, drafts, sketches, and research regarding advertising strategy, specific advertisements, and promotional events. This subseries also contains clippings, sample ads, and promotional materials, such as calendars and pamphlets, and photographic plates of group shots and advertisements. Other promotional items are housed and described in the Memorabilia and Artifacts Series.
      - Advertising and promotions files, (58 folders) (Box 69, 69A, 69B)
    - Community Relations Subseries, 1932-2008 and undated
      Documents NCM's various programs and activities related to community outreach through scholarship support, mentoring programs for youth, and community health programs such as anti-smoking campaigns. Materials consist of event programs, pamphlets, clippings, speeches, photographs, certificates, and leaflets. A substantial portion of the materials are related to the Merrick-Moore Scholarship in the 1930s, including lists of colleges and students, bills, receipts, and correspondence from awardees. Also of note are materials related to the Avery Boys' Club, including a binder belonging to W.J. Kennedy, Jr. Other programs and events are related to the United Negro College Fund, NCCU, the Boy Scouts, Greater Durham Arts Fund, a letter from President Reagan, the 1943 launch of the S.S. Merrick, and Founders' Day celebrations.
      - Community Relations files, (53 folders) (Box 69B, 70, 70A)
    - Financial Statements Subseries, 1966-1968, 1985-1986
      Contains financial reports, annual reports to policyholders, budget statements, advertising expenditures, and periodicals.
      - Financial statements files, (13 folders) (Box 70A, 70B)
    - Heritage Room Subseries, 1975-1983 and undated
      Contains correspondence, clippings, layout plans, and photographs related to the creation of NCM's Heritage Room, a large exhibit on company history.
      - Heritage Room files, (3 folders) (Box 70B)
    - Historical Files Subseries, 1927-2008
      The bulk of the material is related to specific events, such as annual meetings, the ground-breaking ceremony in 1963, and the celebration of NCM's 85th anniversary, centennial, material for tribute honoring Dr. William and Stella Cleland, script material for television episode regarding N.C. Mutual and John Merrick, and various Founders' Days. Materials consist of slides, photographs, clippings, correspondence, programs, print materials, memos, and other planning documents. Also included are historic NCM policies and certificates.
      - Historical files, (20 folders) (Box 70B, 71)
    - Other Correspondence Subseries, 1973-1996
      Files of mixed correspondence concerning the Public Relations Department. The bulk of the files date from 1984-1986. Materials also include solicitations, brochures, and subscription forms. Topics include radio and television stations, interview requests, A.T. Spaulding, Ben Ruffin, and W.J. Kennedy, Jr.
      - Correspondence files, (35 folders) (Box 72, 73)
    - Other Files Subseries, 1984-1986 and undated
      Additional materials created by the Public Relations Department that do not fit in above categories. Topics include office contests, employee benefits, taxation, the donations committee, smoking cessation program files, the new products committee, the lyrics to the company song, and the history of African Methodism. Materials include phone messages, personnel forms, notes, agenda, minutes, memoranda, brochures, correspondence, an architecture showcase book, a drawing of a house, information collected regarding Hispanics, and a memoir about life insurance.
      - Other Public Relations files, (38 folders) (Box 73, 74, 75)
    - Personnel Subseries, 1933-2004
      Files open to research access contain company publicity regarding personnel, including, but not limited to, obituaries, biographies, a list of employee birthdays, and other announcements. Among those profiled are Asa T. Spaulding, C.C. Spaulding, Jr., William Henry Harvey, W.E. Williams, W.E. Coleman, W.D. Hill, J.L. Wheeler, W. Lionel Cook, and Fred R. Moore. Several folders related to the retirement and death of William Kennedy, Jr. contain extensive photographs alongside paper materials. Folders profiling women associated with NCM contain copies of The Whetstone and photographs from the 2000s.
      - Personnel files, (18 folders) (Box 75)
    - Press Coverage and Press Releases Subseries, 1938-2004
      Contains press releases put out by the Public Relations Department and clippings, photocopies, and reprints of articles about NCM and its staff, including entire issues of several mass market magazines.
      - Press coverage and press releases files, (24 folders) (Box 75, 76)
    - Production and Publications Subseries, 1931-1986
      Contains copies of The Review, pages from The Whetstone, ad layouts, proofs, photos, correspondence, notes, memos, and other files relating to Public Relations publishing and printing workflows.
      - Production and publications files, (15 folders) (Box 76)
    - Speeches Subseries, 1953-1973
      Contains copies of speeches, press releases, and interviews with Presidents William J. Kennedy, Jr., J.L. Goodloe, and Asa T. Spaulding. Also includes speeches by various public figures at the home office dedication in 1966.
      - Speeches files, (10 folders) (Box 76, 77)
    - Public Relations Oversize Material
      - Calendar, circa 1940 (Box OV1)
      - Calendar art, A Penny Short, NC Mutual presidents, painting of building, undated
      - Sell-E-Bration poster, 1962 July-Aug.
      - Advertisements, undated (Box OV4)
      - Advertising sketch by Nash, undated (Box OV9)
      - Calendars, 1968-2008, (2 folders) (Box OV10)
      - Calendars, 1930-1939, 1968-1976 (Box OV11)
      - Calendars, 1977-1984, 1990
      - Posters, calendars, art, 1946-1999
      - Advertisements in newspapers and for agents, 1962-1977 (Box OV12)
      - Asa T. Spaulding clippings, 1956-1972
      - Budgets, 1984-1986
      - Clippings, 1950-1991, (3 folders)
      - Programs, advertisements, clippings, 1927-1982
      - Ad ideas and planning, 1972-1982 and undated
      - Advertisements and proofs, 1962-1968, (2 folders) (Box OV13)
      - Durham Arts Council classes, 1986
      - NCCU presidential inauguration, 1968
      - Brown and Bigelow calendar enclosure, 1960
      - NIA 50th anniversary, 1970
      - Newspapers and clippings, 1983-1986, (4 folders)
      - The Whetstone layout, 1993
      - Reproduced proofs with memos, undated, (2 folders) (Box OV14)
      - NCM wall calendars, 1989, 1992, 1999-2006 (Box OV38)
      - Board of Directors, Past and Present, 1946 (Box OV45)
      - Calendar art, A Penny Short painting reproduction, copyright 1936
      - Calendars, 1927-1928, 1936-1938
      - Magazine advertisements (bound), 1975-1978 (Box OV49)
      - Very large posters and advertisements, 1968-2006, (14 items) (Opaperfolder 1-3)
- Corporate History Files, 1900-2005, (2 boxes)
  Assembled by staff of NC Mutual and a former company archivist, these files contain a sampling of the most significant historical documents illustrating the formation of the company, its founders, and its first decade of existence. Materials are varied and include charters and by-laws; early policies, publications and advertisements; significant correspondence; programs, annual statements, and Christmas greetings; items marking milestones in company history; and other unique items. There is also a folder with two charts for 1933 and 1941 ranking the current African American owned life insurance companies, including NCM. Other historical and early items can also be found throughout the collection, especially in the Agency, Memorabilia, Photographic Material, and Print Material Series, and the Office of the President Subseries; early examples of policies from 1902 into the 1930s are found in the Agency Series. Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Bylaws and amendments, 1900-1946 (Box 78)
  - Annual statement, 1908
  - The Mutual Album, 1910
  - Home office postcard, circa 1910
  - Amendment of Charter documents, 1912-1914, (4 folders)
  - Agents' conference, 1920 June
  - Publications and pamphlets, 1920-1923
  - Female employees, 1923-1995
  - Greetings, statements, and advertisements, 1924-1927
  - C.C. Spaulding speeches and other materials, 1926-1935
  - Clippings from newspapers regarding NCM, after 1926-1946, (4 folders)
  - Publications, pamphlets, and advertisements, 1927-1929
  - Biographical sketches of officers and directors, 1927-1969
  - Annual statement, 1928
  - Manuscript and quotations, 1928 and undated
  - Liberia banknote, 1929 Jan. 31
  - Publications, correspondence, advertisements, and statements, 1930-1938
  - Records of life insurance enterprises operated by Negroes, 1933, 1941 (2 charts with data such as assets, founding date)
  - The Negro's Adventure in the Field of Life Insurance, by W.J. Kennedy, Jr., 1934
  - Historical Sketch, by W.J. Kennedy Jr., 1934
  - Thrift Club manual, 1938
  - Charter and amendments, 1938-1946, (4 folders) (Box 79)
  - Chronology, 1938
  - The President's Book, 1939
  - Correspondence, statements, and programs, 1940-1949
  - A Tour of the Home Office, 1945-1955
  - Whaley's Pharmacy grand opening, 1951 Oct. 11
  - Historical summary of provisions governing payment analysis, 1952
  - Publications and memos on NCM history, 1952-2005
  - Proofs from publication on NCM history, undated
  - Speeches, publications, and programs, 1953-1966
  - Bylaws of NCM and other companies, 1957
  - Draft of NCM bylaws, 1958 and undated
  - Bylaws and charter committee, 1963-1971
  - Organizational Survey of the Home Office, 1963 Aug.
  - Presidents' biographical sketches, circa 1990
  - 1909 annual statement, photocopied in 1964 with note from 1983 (Box OV8)
- Digital Media Series, 2000s, (3 boxes)
  Contains diskettes of files and DVDs with photographic images and duplicated historical films, chiefly regarding NC Mutual's history. Titles taken from original media carriers.
  - Diskettes (approx. 30) (Box DIG 1)
  - DVDs (Box DIG 2)
    - 10 DVDs with files of images and documents, and a documentary about "Black Wall Street" in Durham NC
  - 6 DVDs containing copies of films: (Box DIG 3)
    - Dedication, 1966
    - Three color shorts, 1966
    - Dedication, TV, 1966
    - Groundbreaking, circa 1963
    - 75th Anniversary, 1975
    - DC footage, about 1970
- Exhibit Material Series, 1940s, 1960s-2000s, and undated, bulk 1970s-2000s, (25 boxes)
  Houses the components of many exhibits assembled and curated by North Carolina Mutual staff. Mostly consists of black and white or sepia images and captions mounted on thin board, often with velcro backing, which originally formed a large installation in "Heritage Hall" gallery commemorating NCM's history. Other exhibits were created for specific events such as conventions. Most of the images were reproduced from vintage photographs from the early years of the company, many of the original photographs can be found in the Photographic Material Series. Others show officers and employees from throughout NCM's history. Includes color and black and white photographs, signs, labels, and informational panels. Also includes two framed letters of interest: one from Eleanor Roosevelt's secretary, writing in July 1934 subsequent to a visit to NCM by Roosevelt in June of that year, and the other a strongly worded letter written by President Spaulding on improving the company's performance, entitled "Open Letter to Managers," from Berlin, Germany, 1931.
  Many thousands of additional images are housed in the Photographic Materials Series, including original photographs from which the exhibit images were reproduced. Some exhibit materials are in this series as well.
  - Exhibit materials: panels, images, and captions (in original order as received) (Box 80-89)
  - Clipping, policy holders' meeting photographs, 1974, circa 1995 (Box OV1)
  - Exhibit materials: oversize reproductions and captions (in original order as received) (Box OV14-OV22)
  - MEAC exhibit, 1993 (Box OV23)
  - Stairwell Initiative circa 1995
  - NC Mutual building, circa 1980 (Box OV24)
  - Exhibit material, 1943, circa 1963, and undated (Box OV44)
  - Exhibit material (Box OV50-OV51)
- Memorabilia and Artifacts Series, 1923-2008 and undated, bulk 1970s-2000s, (16 boxes)
  Contains a wide variety of items that document recognition of achievements, advertising campaigns, and company and employee milestones throughout the history of NCM. Organized into four subseries: Artifacts, Awards and Memorabilia, Plaques, and Promotional Items.
  - Artifacts Subseries, 1916-2008 and undated
    Material includes a very early papers portfolio probably belonging to E.R. Merrick; a glass ornament; medical supplies; sales logs; an early 20th century leather satchel with the company name (oversize box); and a large 1950s or 1960s-era travel case housing an insurance sales training kit.
    - "Valuable Papers" portfolio and contents, 1916-1919, (6 folders) (Box 90-A)
      Promotional folded portfolio measuring 5.0 x 10.75 inches, stamped on cover with "Valuable Papers, Compliments of North Carolina Mutual and Provident Association." Probably belonged to E.R. Merrick; contained receipts under his name for personal house furnishings, a piano, and baby furniture, among others. Original papers are housed separately from portfolio, whose original filing envelopes are very brittle.
    - "Historical St. Joseph's, 1891" - clear glass flat hexagonal ornament (20th century) (Box 90)
    - Artifacts, (3 large boxes) (Box 91-93)
    - Life insurance training kit in green faux-leather travel case (with transparencies, manuals, and films) (Box 179)
  - Awards and Memorabilia Subseries, 1953-2003 and undated
    The Awards and Memorabilia Subseries houses publicity for insurance coverage and charitable giving, and awards and certificates for NCM employees, as well as awards received by NCM from external organizations. Includes a company award featuring a bronzed shoe belonging to C.C. Spaulding, and two copies of the Merrick-Moore Award. Also includes a 1943 Western Union telegram from then-governor of N.C. Broughton to C.C. Spaulding concerning the launching ceremony of the U.S.S. Merrick (box 90). The first box is arranged in two groups of folders, beginning with memorabilia (chiefly publicity and programs), and then awards.
    - Printed materials and papers, (11 folders) (Box 90)
    - Framed and artifactual items, (2 large boxes) (Box 94-95)
  - Plaques Subseries, 1959-2008 and undated, (7 large boxes) (Box 96-102)
    Two groups of awards: plaques marking achievements within the company of its employees and officials, and plaques received by NCM honoring the company for its contributions to the community, commemorating its lifetime membership in the NAACP, and other milestones.
  - Promotional Items Subseries, circa 1950-2002 and undated
    Consists of both printed material and artifacts, including holiday cards, pocket calendars, fans, match books series with leaders from the civil rights movement, blank baby books, and bookmarks, among many other items.
    - Promotional NCM paper fans, circa 1960s-1998 and undated (Box 90-A)
    - Printed materials, (9 folders) (Box 90)
    - Artifactual items, (1 large box) (Box 103)
  - Memorabilia and Artifacts Series Oversize Boxes
    - Certificates, 1962-2005 (Box OV9)
    - Article About Mutual Plaza Dedication (deframed), 1966
    - Programs, awards, and certificates, 1923-2004 (Box OV23)
    - A.M. Best Certification of Financial Strength Rating, 2006, Feb. 10
    - Prudential Insurance plaque, 1967 (Box OV24)
    - Carrier bag, early 20th c.? (Box OV25)
    - Advertising Federation award, 1974 (Box OV26)
    - Certificate from UNC President commemorating NCM's centennial, 1998
    - "An Album of the American Family," 1980
    - Federal Housing Administration Award, 1959, June 1
    - "Official Welcome to Baltimore" certificate, 1998, Sep. 14
    - Durham County Board of County Commissioners resolution commemorating NCM's 95th anniversary, 1993, Oct. 11
    - Durham resolution honoring NCM 100th anniversary (framed), 1998 (Box OV45)
    - Plaques, 1991-1997 and undated (Box OV46)
    - NCM visitor register, 1924-1955 (Box OV48)
- Other Organizations Series, 1927-2008 and undated, (9 boxes)
  Contains documents from companies which NCM acquired, and companies with which NCM shared a relationship (or from which it obtained information for planning). These companies include: Wright Mutual Insurance Company, Lincoln National Life Foundation, Inc., the National Insurance Association (NIA), NCM Capital, and Mortgage Company of Durham.
  [Box 104 contains fragile material and is slated for preservation photocopying. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material.]
  - Lincoln National Life Foundation, Inc. Subseries, 1973-1975
    Created to administer the Lincoln National Life Museum, the Foundation provided an avenue for charitable, tax-exempt contributions of Lincoln memorabilia to the museum. It appears that the NCM Corporate Planning department requested information from the Lincoln National Life Foundation regarding its annual report and bylaws in 1975.
    - Lincoln National Life Foundation documents, 1973-1975 (Box 104)
  - Mortgage Company of Durham Subseries, 1929-1941
    Founded in 1929 by C.C. Spaulding, E.R. Merrick, and R.L. McDougald to provide greater financial independence for black businesses in Durham, N.C. Although this company stood as a separate corporate entity from NCM, many of the members of the Executive Committee were leaders at NCM, and the company was somewhat connected with NCM in practice. The material consists of the early minutes of the Executive Committee of the Mortgage Company of Durham.
    [Fragile and slated for preservation photocopying. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material.]
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of the Mortgage Company of Durham, 1929-1941, (2 folders) (Box 104)
  - National Insurance Association Subseries, 1927, 1951-1964, 1975-2008, and undated
    Established in 1921 as the National Negro Insurance Association (later renamed National Insurance Association or NIA), and was created in order to promote and represent the mutual interests of insurance companies that were owned and operated by African Americans. C.C. Spaulding was elected as the first president of the association and NCM has remained one of the largest member companies of the organization to the present. NCM employees have regularly served on the Board of Directors and as officers for the NIA.
    - Assorted printed material and miscellaneous documents, 2005-2008 (Box 104)
    - NIA brochure, 2007 and undated
    - NIA: (Box 105)
    - Assorted convention planning material, 2006-2007
    - NIA annual convention programs, 2002-2004, 2006-2008
    - 44th Institute in Agency Management, 2000
    - Audit report, 1979-1980
    - By-laws and related items, 1927, 1951-1964, 1991-1999
    - Committees and other NIA files, 1991-1996
    - Conferences and other pamphlets, 1988, 1998-2002
    - Excerpts on notable African Americans, Little Known History of the Negro, undated
    - NIA corporate policies, plans, job descriptions, 1975 and undated
    - NIA tax files, 1985, 1991-1997
    - NIA tax files and IRS correspondence, 1986-1991, (2 folders)
    - Resumes, 1981-1982 and undated
    - Surveys, studies, workshops, and other material, 2000-2001
    - Various NIA pamphlets, newsletters, correspondence, and printed material, 1989-1998 and undated
    - NIA Golden Anniversary scrapbook, 1970 (Box 106)
    - Poster of NIA presidents, circa 1970 (Box OV1)
    - 66th National Insurance Month posters, 2000 May (Box OV2)
  - NCM Capital Subseries, 1986-1994 and undated
    Maceo Sloan of North Carolina Mutual founded NCM Capital in 1986. NCM is a parent company of NCM Capital. Contents include Board records, reports, and general business files.
    - NCM Capital miscellaneous business files, 1987-1988, (3 folders) (Box 106)
    - NCM Capital Board and business files, 1986-1989 and undated, (26 folders) (Box 107)
    - NCM Capital reports and correspondence, 1989-1994 and undated, (22 folders) (Box 108)
    - NCM Capital correspondence, reports, minutes, and business files, 1986-1990 and undated, (18 folders) (Box 109)
  - Wright Mutual Insurance Company Subseries, 1942-1967, 1985-2000
    Records of the Wright Mutual Insurance Company, acquired by NC Mutual in 2000.
    - Foreclosure proceedings and legal research, 1985-1993 (Box 109)
    - Legal documents, 1994
    - Appraisal for home office, 1988 (Box 110)
    - Board of Directors
      - Minutes, 1990-1999, (4 folders)
      - Notices, 1998
    - Certificates of Authority and Certificates of Interest, 1963, 1967, 1993-1999
    - Complaints, 1994-1998
    - Correspondence from Mich. Treasury Dept. and Mich. Dept. of Insurance, 1942-1946
    - Dreifus Insurance Exchange Agency, 1990-1998
    - Kaid Almadrahi case, 1990-1992
    - Miscellaneous Insurance Coverage for Wright Mutual, 1999
    - Notice to policyholders of NC Mutual merger and late policy payment notices, 1999, 2000 Dec.
    - Omni-Care Health Plan, 1997-1999
    - Photos of Board of Directors and information booklet, 1987
    - Lincoln National Pension benefit quote summaries and benefit payouts, 1980-1987
    - Pension plan, 1987-1999
    - Amended bylaws, 1967, 1990 (Box 111)
    - Articles of Association, 1942
    - Certificates of Amendment, 1945, 1959, 1966, 1985
    - Certificate of Authority, 1942-1944
    - Cynthia Thomas-Riley case, 1994-1997, (3 folders)
    - Deed for home office, 1961
    - Foreclosure documents and notes, 1975-1993, (2 folders)
    - Landlord-tenant decisions, 1991-1994, (2 folders)
    - Legal complaints against Wright Mutual, 1991-1993
    - Mortgage foreclosure proceedings, 1991-1993
    - Papers regarding incorporation and connection with Pilgrims Mutual Aid Society, 1942-1944
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee minutes, 1954-1973, (9 folders) (Box 112)
    - General contents of Board of Directors and Executive Committee minutes binders, copyrighted 1945
    - Wright Mutual Insurance Company brochure, circa 1963
- Photographic Materials Series, 1888-2008 and undated, (22 boxes)